[Music]
it's the oerman report and now here is
investigator Ed
oerman okay welcome to the oerman report
I am your host private investigator at
oerman tonight we have again forget it
tonight's a blockbuster show we have
John
kiraku and he is a former CIA agent and
he's the author of The Reluctant spy and
uh he pretty much just got out of prison
uh for uh being like a whistleblower uh
so John are you there I sure am thanks
for having me thank you so much I'm
really excited to have you on here uh
especially the little chat we had off
the air uh so give us an idea who is
John CaRu and and what is your story
well um I joined the CIA in January of
1990 as an analyst working on the Middle
East and uh loved that job uh did it for
7 and A2 years and then decided I was
ready for something new and I switch to
operations also within the
CIA and uh did that for another 7 and a
half years so after the September 11th
attacks I became the chief of CIA uh
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
and in that capacity led a raid on the
night of March 28th 2002 that turned out
to be the biggest counterterrorism raid
in CIA history which still stands we
captured abuu beta
who we believed at the time was the
number three in al-Qaeda and we caught
51 other Al-Qaeda Fighters I went home
from Pakistan in uh in late
2002 and was asked when I got home if I
wanted to be certified in the use of
what they called uh enhanced
interrogation techniques I called them
torture techniques and I declined to be
trained uh I left the CIA in 2004 went
into the private sector for a while then
I went to the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee and I was the senior
investigator for that committee and I
was the senior intelligence advisor to
the chairman John KY uh but in 2007 I
went on ABC News and um and I said three
things that really changed the course of
my life I said that the CIA was
torturing its prisoners I said that
torture was official US government
policy and I said that that policy had
been approved and signed by the
president president now the President
George W bush had said earlier in the
week with his eyes right on the camera
he said we do not torture and I said
that the president is a liar and so that
resulted in a four-year-long uh FBI
investigation I was finally charged with
five felonies uh including three counts
of Espionage for uh saying that we were
torturing
prisoners uh those Espionage counts were
dropped I took a plea to a lesser charge
I did 23 months in a federal prison not
in a country club prison but in a real
honest to God prison and um and got out
this
February how old are you now I'm 51 just
turned 51 wow 51 okay that's not easy
time going into 30 months in prison 47
years no no not not easy time at all and
I'll tell you what you know my only
exposure to prison had been watching
MSNBC at 11:00 at night um so I I really
didn't know what to expect and I thought
I was going to a minimum security Work
Camp uh that's what the judge had
recommended that's what the prosecutors
had agreed to uh in fact the the Bureau
of Prisons does whatever it uh it
pleases and so uh as soon as I arrived
they they took me around to the back and
put me in the actual prison rather than
in the minimum security Camp yeah
sometimes when I'm watching Rachel matow
I feel like I'm in maximum
security I'm sorry I can't watch those
shows anymore okay so you just got now
uh how old were you when you went into
the
CIA um I was young let's see I was
25 when I joined the CIA and what did
you do before that um I was in grad
school I I got a Bachelor's degree in in
uh Middle Eastern studies and I was
working on a on a master's degree in
legislative affairs when one of my
professors uh who liked my writing style
uh asked me to stay after class one day
and uh to make a long story short it
turned out he was actually undercover as
a professor he was working as what used
to be called a CIA spotter looking for
grad students who would fit into the
agency's culture and so um he recruited
me into the CIA right out of graduate
school you know there must be a lot of
that because I know I've had I've had a
lot of CIA guys on the show and uh uh I
I believe I've heard that story before
that they were recruited Yeah by a
professor yeah it actually used to be
quite it it really you know until
1992 or 93 with the passage of the Equal
Employment Opportunity Act it was pretty
much the only real way to get into the
CIA you had to be noticed you had to be
spotted I mean it's like it's like being
at the soda fountain at whatever that
famous uh drugstore was in Hollywood you
know if you wanted to be an actor so um
you know there there used to be senior
Cia officers under cover at important
universities all around the country
and I just you know was lucky enough to
to have one as my grad school adviser
now so but now but you had no plans uh
even though you were taking these
foreign languages uh you had no plans to
go to the CIA or something like that no
I was thinking that I I would probably
end up on Capitol Hill or maybe take the
foreign service exam I knew I wanted to
work in foreign affairs uh doing
something but I hadn't really given the
CIA any thought until they approached me
okay gotcha now now you said you were at
first you were an analyst or something
like that yeah I was for the first half
of my career and the the analytic jobs
at the CIA are a lot of fun if
especially if you're an introvert
because you're going to sit in your
cubicle nine or 10 hours a day and think
the big thoughts and write important
papers and send those papers to the
White House and hope that the president
reads them and comments on them um but
you know after doing that year in year
out working on Iraq you know year after
year after year it it wears you down and
I I thought boy I'm I'm 30 years old
there's got to be more than more to life
than this so uh I decided you know I I
spoke Arabic I spoke Greek and um it was
time for something exciting and so on
the strength of those two languages I
was able to switch over to
counterterrorism
operations and this is around 30 years
old now so you must have been in pretty
good shape right yeah I I was in pretty
good shape I I wasn't uh former military
but I I was thin and young and strong
and happy to jump out of the plane and
be trained and everything else and you
know the friends of mine were like are
you sure you want to do this this is
going to be rough this is going to be
like being in the military at least
through training and I said yeah I know
yeah I can I can tough it out for
whatever it was six or eight months at
the time and I ended up doing very well
and I enjoyed it very
much a and because right because the
operations you were doing as part of the
CIA were actually military combat
operations right well no um they became
military or paramilitary combat
operations after September 11th before
September 11th it was you know much more
old school it was much more
sophisticated uh where we have something
called the asset recruitment cycle it's
it's every officer has to spot assess
develop and recruit um an agent in order
to get promoted right you have to
recruit spot to steal secrets and you
spot these people depending on what your
target is or what kind of job you're
doing at diplomatic cocktail parties or
wherever I mean any number of of
different scenarios after September
11th it really did change to to
paramilitary operations where you know
you're you're wearing whatever special
forces where and you parachute into
something and you shoot the place up and
you grab the bad guy but before
September 11th that's really not what
the CIA was right before it sounds more
like Amway or like you're recruiting
people to come in underneath you but you
know pretty much it was the same idea
now you have to establish a a
relationship with somebody with your
target right you have to establish a
rapport um to the point where you become
so close to that person or at least that
person thinks that you're close uh to
the point where he's going to commit
Espionage for you he's going to commit
treason for you because he likes you I
mean there's certainly other motivators
money Revenge
ideology but the real basis of the
relationship is
friendship wow it's it's almost like
you're a con man or a cult you know I
I've
said years in interviews that that those
of us who were in operations or are in
operations uh right now you you're
trained to lie and you lie every day and
you lie all day and you live a lie you
just have to know when to turn it off at
the end of the day a lot of guys can't
and so you know the CIA has a Sky High
divorce rate um but uh yeah you you are
very well trained as a professional
liar okay fascinating okay so now uh and
you said that you you went you went to
Afghanistan and you captured this guy
who was this guy you captured in in
Pakistan this was Abu Zeda
we thought at the time that he was the
number three in al-Qaeda in fact he had
never actually joined Al-Qaeda but his
job was to provide al-qaeda's um
logistical support logistical leadership
he created al-qaeda's two training camps
in southern Afghanistan um if you needed
a false passport or you needed a plane
ticket Abu zua was the guy if you needed
a safe house or way to uh to get from
point A to point B across the border you
went to Abu Zeda so although he had
never formally joined Al-Qaeda he had
never pledged Fieldy to AMA Bin Laden he
was al-qaeda's go-to guy for
Logistics that's interesting so now but
you hear these stories over here in the
United States that they're hanging out
in caves and stuff like that yeah not
true okay then give us I I don't know
how that rumor ever got started that
they were living in caves that the whole
Cave Story never made sense to me
because I mean these guys are just like
everybody else you can you can rough it
for for only so long you know people
used to ask me where do you think Bin
Laden is and I said I used to say I
think Bin Laden is comfortable in a
house in a major city somewhere and I'll
tell you why because these guys always
thought that we thought that they were
hiding in the tribal areas because we
can't get to the tribal areas except
with the use of drones in fact we knew
that they were all in major cities and
it was this reverse reverse
psychology so when they're in the cities
thinking that we're looking for them in
the countryside they tend to be a little
bit more sloppy especially with their
electronic communications cellphones
emails stuff like that and then they're
easier to catch when they're in the city
I mean we caught abua in a major city we
caught khed shik Muhammad in a major
city he was The Mastermind of the 911
attacks we caught uh abdurahim Ines in a
major city he was The Mastermind of the
coal bombing we caught Ramsey b aib in a
major city and then of course you know
Bin Laden was in the Pakistani version
of West Point in a major city yeah right
now now what do you make of that you
know because uh you'd think that these
guys would be on our side right or on
your side you know on the CIA side uh
well I always said that the Pakistani
intelligence service isi was really two
separate organizations the the guys that
I was working with were were just
fantastic I mean they were all trained
in the UK
uh they all went through Sandhurst and
British police training and they were
really great they were great
counterterrorism Partners but isi is
also the same organization that created
the Taliban you know when when Benazir
BH was the Prime Minister of Pakistan
she created the Taliban see Taliban is a
word in both Arabic and in Udu that
means uh students the the singular is
Talib and the plural is Taliban which
means students and these students were
studying in madrasas in Islamic private
Islamic schools in Pakistan and they
were they were Afghan Nationals so the
pakistanis were running trucks across
Afghanistan to Iran so that they could
sell their goods in Iran and the um
trucks were being hijacked as they were
crossing Pakistan so benzir B got this
group of students together and said I
want you to ride along in the trucks you
know with weapons and if anybody tries
to hijack the trucks fight them off so
as these trucks would cross Afghanistan
the Taliban were able to secure
individual uh villages along the Route
and that's how they ended up taking over
Pakistan so benzero and isi created the
Taliban they trained the Taliban they
financed the Taliban they armed the
Taliban and at the same time other isi
officers are working with us to fight
the T
so there was this disconnect within the
Pakistani intelligence service you could
trust some of them you couldn't trust
others you just had to play your cards
well okay now I I recall I forget who
was president at the time but I I recall
that the Taliban come to the United
States and it was like a big press
conference and it was revealed that
their lobbyist was the daughter of one
of the CIA directors are you familiar
with that
story yeah I do remember that story and
I I recall she was based in New Jersey I
think it was do you remember which CIA
CIA director that was yeah I don't but I
I recall it being sort of a
non-controversial issue at the time
because you know we we never had any
beef with a Taliban historically now
some of those members of the Taliban
especially the older ones were jihadis
from the from the uh the the war against
the Soviets and of course we we financed
them we trained them we armed them we
gave them Stinger missiles and every
year or two they would come to the
United States they would meet with
President Reagan they would be FedEd in
Washington then they'd go back to uh to
Afghanistan so we had this relationship
with at least some of these these people
and until Bin Laden went to
Afghanistan we sort of saw the Taliban
is not our fight if if they were going
to trample 's rights well you know we
had no National interest there it was
none of our business it wasn't until
they provided safe haven for bin Laden
that we decided this was going to be a
problem what do you make of Bin Laden
okay there some people say that outright
that he was CIA and they had I think his
name was Osman or something like that
Ben Osman you know he had another name
you know yeah and that
uh and then you got all this stuff about
how um his Brothers connected up with
the the Carlile group and was actually
meeting with bush the the day of 9/11 oh
oh sure but but that's not scandalous
That's Not Unusual first of all Bin
Laden was never trained by the CIA he
was never a CIA Source he was never
armed by the CIA he didn't actually go
to Afghanistan from Saudi Arabia until
after the CIA um stopped funding and
training uh the Afghan mujahedin so
that's kind of a common misnomer a lot
of people think that the CIA trained Bin
Laden or created Bin Laden that's just
not true um you're talking about the
extended Bin Laden family the bin Laden
family is a very honorable family in
Saudi Arabia they're incredibly wealthy
you know 10 figure kind of wealthy
because the old man abdurahman Bin Laden
who originally moved to Saudi Arabia
from Yemen um created what became the
Kingdom's largest construction firm and
and his firm would make would would do
the biggest projects they would build
airports and and hospitals and ports and
shopping malls and stuff like that
so the old man insisted that that most
if not all of his uh children be
educated in the west um they travel to
the United States all the time they own
property in Beverly Hills and in Miami
Beach and you know they're very
Americanized it's just that that one son
of AMA was for whatever reason
radicalized and instead of going into
the family business along with his 113
other
brothers um he he went to Afghanistan to
make
Jihad and and and what do you make of uh
people who say well he he died prior to
the to the story that U that we hear in
the news about him ding yeah that's just
nonsense I mean you know we we we would
get these reports at the CIA all the
time that Bin Laden had kidney fail
he was on dialysis inside a cave uh he
had some kind of spinal disorder we were
always getting these these uh medical uh
rumors reported back to us and and none
of them ended up uh to be true but no he
he was in perfectly fine Health except
for some arthritis um he had an ongoing
hip problem um but he he was he was
healthy enough to wage war against the
United States until the day died
okay
um oh boy oh okay I almost
forgot set my mind for a second what
what do you make of these stories about
the the the Navy Seals uh who are part
of that operation now all of a sudden
they're all dead in U in helicopter
crashes and stuff right you know that's
actually not uncommon um being a Navy
SEAL is one of the most dangerous
professions in the world and um
we're not talking specifically about the
Navy Seals who were directly uh involved
in the bin Laden takedown being killed
we're talking about Navy Seals from
their broader unit so we're talking
about you know 100 120 150 seals so for
for a number of seals a high number of
seals to be killed um whether it's in
accidents or in combat is actually very
sadly uh
common okay so ni so you're saying that
the when we hear these stor about how
the Navy Seals who killed Bin Laden now
most of them are dead it's you're saying
it's not the actual same guys it's just
the guys in the same no not at all okay
it's not the same guys uhuh
interesting okay um yeah let me
interrupt you you know when when people
talk about SEAL Team Six um or you see
SEAL Team Six in movies you you imagine
a dozen or dozen a half guys that make
up SEAL Team Six in fact it's several
hundred guys that make up SEAL Team Six
and it's you know from those several
hundred uh that that we find these these
individuals who have been killed in
accidents or killed in
combat now what about uh the stories
about the the funeral like this this
ocean funeral and then even some uh
congressmen who saw pictures and stuff
like that said it looked like it was
fake and and then even the White House
had to kind of step back on some of the
official story around that what do you
make of that yeah you know I don't know
what to believe I
I think he probably was buried at Sea
the way they they say he was buried at
Sea maybe some of the details are wrong
because God knows the White House of
story changes constantly uh every time
this comes up but I I don't I just don't
see any conspiracy related to it I I see
a bunch of people talking out of school
and and pretending to know the details
of what happened when in fact they don't
really know the details and I think
that's why the story tends to change but
I do think that Bin Laden was was killed
uh in whatever it was May of 2011 I
think he really was buried at Sea um and
I I'm just not sure that the details are
really that important now now how about
when you were in CIA were you ever
involved in like U promoting false
stories and and uh no you know I there
there is such a thing as a false flag
operation false flag operations are very
very um difficult and there are a lot of
moving parts and you have to have a lot
of people that buy in to the conspiracy
um but but we really didn't use those
very often because they were so
complicated it wasn't until you know
just
recently you know where people have
started to email me or Facebook me or
contact me on Twitter about false flag
operations and I even have one friend
who just thinks that every event in life
is a false flag operation and it's just
it just seems so Preposterous to me
because they are so labor intensive and
so difficult to carry out that just
doesn't make sense to me yeah I I I
sympathize with you I get those emails
too they mean well they really do but I
know and you kind of can't blame some
people for being paranoid you know you
can't blame people for being par no you
can't you know when when you have a
government that's not transparent right
when you have a government that that
pretends to tell the American people the
whole story uh related to these to these
terrorist uh you know operations and
then the story changes you can't blame
people for being for being suspicious of
the government line right right and and
you said now we have a government that
tortes people and says it's okay exactly
and that denied it and denied it and
denied it you know I said this I said
this the other day in an oped that I
wrote everything that the government has
told us about torture since 2002 has
been a lie so why would you believe them
now you know George W bush said in 2002
we don't torture and he said it again in
three and four and five and six and
seven but the week that I went on ABC
News he looked right in the camera and
he said we do not torture and I remember
saying to my wife that is a bald-faced
lie he's just lying to the American
people and George Tennant said the same
thing in 2005 on 60 Minutes he came off
in that segment like he was unhinged he
was practically shouting it we don't
torture we don't torture we don't
torture well of course we
torture and what makes it worse is not
only are there us laws that that
prohibit
torture but there are international
treaties and conventions that the US is
a signatory to and in some cases that
the US
wrote and bullied other countries into
signing and then we violate those
International treaties and conventions
by torturing let me tell you another
thing in January anuary of 1968 The
Washington Post ran a front page
photograph of a of an American Soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner when that photo was published
the Secretary of Defense Robert mcamera
um ordered an
investigation the soldier was arrested
and he was charged with torture and he
was convicted and sent to prison so why
was torture illegal in
1968 but it wasn't illegal in 2002 cuz
the law didn't change there was no there
was no Amendment to the law Banning
torture saying well okay now it's okay
you know there was no law that said well
water boarding is not torture cold cells
not torture sleep deprivation is not
torture the law didn't
change but we just had a group of
attorneys in the Justice Department who
decided that they were going to twist
the law uh to do what they wanted and
that's exactly what happened yeah this
is really you know you and I are the
same age you know uh and and this this
is such a a disturbing uh that even that
we're even talking about this and and
that people are excusing it and uh it's
really uh shattering it is it is you
know I I I consider myself to be a
patriot and not just a patriot but a
patriot who who spent 20 years serving
my country in some of the most awful and
dangerous places on Earth and I know
that my country is better than this my
country shouldn't be waterboarding
people or or forcing hummus up their
rectums or murdering them in the middle
of of uh interrogations or to make
matters worse droning American citizens
overseas who have not been charged with
a crime who have not had the right to
meet their accusers in court that's not
the America that I know and love I don't
know where this came from okay well then
then coming from where you are right now
today and and just having sered 30
months I believe right 30 months yes do
you still consider yourself a patriot do
you still support the Iraq War the the
Afghanistan war do you still uh where
are you now well I I am a patriot I
never I never supported the Iraq War
though I never thought that was a just
war and I even spent a good amount of uh
space in my in my first book about it U
that was a war of choice that was a war
of Revenge for the family uh but yeah I
I always supported the Afghan War I
don't anymore because because the the
whole point of the Afghan war was to
defeat Al-Qaeda and we defeated Al-Qaeda
by the middle of 2003 so the rest of
this since 2003 this has been nation
building which is never a good idea but
yeah I I am still a patriot and I want
my September 10th country back and what
about the ruined by by George W bush and
by Barack Obama equally what about the
overthrow in
Libya see this is another thing Kadafi
was a was a very bad guy but we actually
had a very healthy working relationship
with with Qaddafi and Qaddafi hated
Al-Qaeda as much as we did so flipping
sides at the last minute like we did to
overthrow kadashi was a was a terrible
policy error I mean look at the place
now it's it's literally Anarchy it's
chaos right well you say it's a policy
area but according to Wesley Clark he
says that's the plan all along to cause
these stabilization to cause chaos see
this is the thing and and West Clark I
mean West Clark was a four-star general
um he ought to know U what he's talking
about so I if that's if that's the
policy I think that's an incredibly
shortsighted policy because invariably
where there's a power vacuum we get
dragged in and when we get dragged into
something like this like we did in
Lebanon for example in the 1980s we
can't get ourselves back out again
do do you think there's a motive to get
us back out when the when these
companies like how Burton are making all
this money on laundry and and it just
it's unbelievable the kind of money
they're making over there that that's a
really important point I never believed
that until I'm going to say the last
four or five years and I I've come to
the conclusion that that we need
economically we need for war to be a
permanent thing yeah and already the
American people are sort of numb to the
idea of war and part because we have an
all volunteer
military uh and I think that's why we're
not seeing demonstrations in the streets
I mean already Afghanistan it's the
longest warn American history it's twice
as long more than actually it's more
than well now it's it's three times as
long as World War II was and uh you know
nobody's really upset about
this so now John where did
um the torturing get started was this at
Guantanamo was this in Abu grabe where
did you it it was before Abu grabe and
um actually before Guantanamo uh abua
was the first
highlevel uh Al-Qaeda related prisoner
that we had captured and
so you know at the time and when I say
at the time I mean I mean immediately
after the September 11th attacks Osama
Bin Laden released a statement in which
he said
that Al-Qaeda was planning another
attack that would dwarf September 11th
and we were panicked at the thought
because September 11th was a was a
disaster it was an intelligence failure
it was just an an across theboard you
know American failure so we were worried
about this this what they call the
ticking Time Bomb
scenario and
so cia's leadership believed that abua
had information related to whatever this
upcoming attack was or was going to be
in fact there there was no upcoming
attack uh he just said it to panic us
and and he
succeeded so a decision was made at CIA
headquarters that we were going to come
up with these with these torture
techniques it was a list of of something
like 10 different torture techniques and
um and they sent this list to the
justice department which approved it and
then it went to the lawyers at the
National Security Council they approved
it from there it went to the um National
Security adviser who was she was cond
condesa rice at the time she approved it
and sent it to the president well nobody
in the cia's leadership thought the
president was going to approve this
because it was clearly torture and sure
enough he approved it and I remember
sitting in a meeting with the deputy
director of the CIA um the day after the
memo the signed memo came into
headquarters and the deputy director
said something like three times during
the course of our conversation I can't
believe the president signed that memo I
can't believe it and that's how the
torture regime started
Guantanamo I mean we we really didn't
even how should I say this guantan was
supposed to be a temporary stop see we
were we were capturing people so quickly
and we were capturing so many of them
especially after the fall of torab Bora
in October 2001
that we needed someplace to just park
them long enough uh for us to put all
the paperwork together and then send
them to the United States to stand trial
because September 11th was still an
ongoing open criminal investigation
guantan was never supposed to be
permanent they were supposed to stay
there only long enough for us to then
send them onward to the states for uh
for trial and of course nobody ever went
on trial and here we are 14 years later
and we're still talking about whether or
not we should close
Guantanamo you know my next guest
tonight uh Michael uh bo the attorney uh
and and the story is about how the
Marines turned a blind eye to child sex
abuse did you ever run across any of
that over there yeah in Afghanistan you
actually run into it with some
regularity it's this weird thing in
Afghan culture that if a boy um does not
yet have whiskers if he hasn't yet
reached puberty um you can have sex with
him uh it's specific to to U Sunni
Muslims and uh that's why a lot of a lot
of Taliban uh would would rape young
boys it's just this weird perverted
cultural thing that they have what about
the stories we heard of of uh young boys
being raped at Abu gra in front of their
parents as part of
interrogation um to the best of my
understanding that didn't happen
although I mean it's almost as bad uh
it's my understanding that some of our
soldiers threatened prisoners with that
that if you don't talk we're going to
rape your children if you don't talk
we're going to rape your your wife or
we're going to rap rape your children in
front of your wife we'll rape your wife
in front of you you know that kind of
thing now that that's also a violation
of law both US law and and uh the um
United Nations convention on torture uh
but we we actually did that kind of
thing in Abu grave at least threatened
it I mean well if you look at some of
the pictures that came out of Abu have
you been to Abu grave what do you know
for no no I've not been to ABR okay but
you you've seen some of those pictures
that came out of there oh yeah they got
horrific naked guys and naked guys in a
pyramid you know it's Way Beyond the
naked guys with electrical wires to
their scrotums you know we we did
horrible things to people over there
whatever hor things that that aren't
that aren't appropriate in any
circumstance whether in war or peace or
even effective to get uh confessions out
of people and really that's the most
important point they're not effective in
any way in getting confessions or in
getting any kind of intelligence you
know we know now from both the Senate
torture report and the CIA inspector
General's report that was released in
the spring of 2009 that torture never
worked that that CIA interrogators never
gathered any actionable intelligence and
that no American lives were saved and
and let me add one more thing about that
too you hear a lot of people now saying
well it was just the Senate intelligence
committee Democrats that signed on to
that report let me remind those
naysayers that the Senate Democrats and
the Senate intelligence committee
investigators used primary source
documents that is original CIA
intelligence cables from the field to
write that report so there is no
rebuttal you know there is no excuse
torture didn't work it never works it
didn't save any American
Life did you watch the hearings
yesterday I did okay so did I the whole
thing all day long now now what do you
make of that it seems to me that
something more was going on down there
with the CIA compound across from this
uh you know you've heard the rumors
right about gun running and these kind
of things what do you make of that yeah
I think there's actually some evidence
of gun
running yeah you know this this whole
idea of gun running um has been a
problem really since the very beginning
of the uprising against
Gaddafi already already Libya is kind of
a No Man's Land because it's its borders
aren't clearly defined the desert is
constantly shifting Libya is an
intensely tribally based society so you
can't really really you know people in
Libya never really trust their central
government and then you've got vast
numbers of weapons uh changing hands so
you know who's involved I'm not sure
we're ever going to really get to the
bottom of that story was the CIA
involved were the British involved were
the Egyptians involved I don't think
we'll ever really
know and it doesn't seem like that these
hearings are even trying to find
out yeah you know there are so many
legitimate issues that we could be
talking about related to Benghazi or or
Libya more broadly um and instead it
just devolved into this this political
thing between Hillary Clinton and the
Republicans on the committee I don't
think anybody did the American people
any service by allowing this to become
political when there are some very
important intelligence issues at play
here and you know I I saw a thing on the
news the other day saying that in the
years that George W Bush was was uh
president something like 60 attacks
there were 60 attacks around the world
against American embassies and
consulates including I forget what you
know half a dozen or a dozen deaths and
we've never investigated any of those
maybe we should maybe we should
investigate every time there's an attack
on a on an American Embassy or consulate
or anytime American Personnel overseas
are killed it shouldn't be political it
shouldn't be partisan it should be
something we're doing so that we can
improve the protection of our own
facilities and our own people yeah there
were half a dozen NB attacks that
weekend it was demonstration but they
breached yeah so yeah why aren't we why
aren't we investigating that well good
question you know it's a circus that's
why look at Donald Trump we gotta wa all
that all that it's a circus over there
right now man that's right I wish it
would torture me I wish you I can't take
any more of this what do you make of uh
we just had this thing in the news just
in the past week where this guy this Fox
news commentator was claiming to be a
CIA what's going on with that man you
know it's funny to me I have run into so
many people over the years who claim to
be agency right and um and you can spot
them from a mile away because they they
get the lingo wrong uh I interviewed a
guy one time he I was working in the
private sector after I left the CIA and
I was working um in competitive
intelligence business intelligence and
so this guy applied for a job and and on
his resume he said he was a CIA officer
and I thought oh okay well I'm going to
I'm going to take this guy to lunch and
uh you know maybe we have some friends
in comment I'll see if he's any good so
I took him to lunch and I said to him
listen I said it's it's not clear from
your resume whether you were from the
director of operations or the director
of intelligence uh so where did you work
and he said oh both I was I was
both and I said well that's kind of
impossible you have to be from one or
the other oh he says I was operations I
said oh okay uh so where did you work he
said oh I was counterterrorism I said
well that's great I was counter
terrorism what division were you in and
he just looked at me with this blank
this blank
ha and I said you made all this up
didn't you and he's like I'm really
sorry I really need this job and I said
okay thanks nice meeting you and that
was the end of it so this guy on Fox
News you know he said he was like
something like outside paramilitary
Special Operations well those are just
meaningless words there is no such
position as outside paramilitary Special
Operations I mean it it sounds like very
woo very intriguing and it's it's all
these buzzwords but but it doesn't mean
anything there is no such position and
so you know the first time I heard this
guy say I thought absolutely no way he's
CIA he may have been a contractor you
know he may have been inflating what he
did but there's no way this guy was see
and then sure enough he
wasn't okay but now first how do he get
away with that you know why doesn't the
CIA step right away and say this guy's
not the he's not the real
deal yeah he's not the real deal the the
real shame about this whole thing is
that apparently this son of a gun was
able to trick people at at DOD into
giving him a security clearance yeah
just because he told them he had been
CIA this guy went overseas to
Afghanistan to advise are generals on
strategy because he said he was from the
CIA well I can tell you any CIA officer
I've ever worked with could peg this guy
in five seconds and say this guy's
making the whole thing up well okay you
know we spend a lot of money to support
the CIA right yeah do they have TV
sets do they have cable news couldn't
they turn on their TV over there and see
this guy on TV and say hey does anybody
know this guy yeah and we all do that
right like every once in a while if I'm
flipping through Fox News I'll see
somebody like well I won't even say his
name but I'll see somebody I I served
with and I'm like oh hey he ended up on
Fox news good for him or else I saw I
saw a former boss of mine on CNBC and I
was like oh hey there's Mike he's on
CNBC good for Mike but this guy I mean
you would think that somebody would say
you know gez I'm paramilitary at CIA I
never saw this guy before or even active
duty right now CIA would they must be
checking to see what information
slipping out through Fox news or through
the news you think yeah you would think
I I would have you're you're exactly
right I would have expected somebody at
the CIA to call Fox News and say hey
this guy's an imposter and especially
when we know for a fact that
intelligence uh departments have a lot
of control over what goes on in the
media and the news and movies absolutely
yeah I got some guys here I'm working
with Pierce Redmond and Tom Seer they
they they get the FIA records of how the
military and the defense department is
so involved in the mov industry it's
into such detail you wouldn't believe
it's embarrassing yeah so now how did
this guy get away with this for so long
I don't know it's I I hope that this is
an anomaly no it's I hope that somehow
for whatever reason this guy slipped
through the cracks I will add though
that his message on Fox News was always
solidly Pro CIA solidly Pro dood and I
wonder if people at the CIA did know
that he was an impostor but figured well
you know he's saying all the right
things so we're not going to
object okay yeah because because I you
know in my business I run into a lot of
these guys who make these kind of claims
in my business as a pi and also as a
radio host I run into these crackpots
all day long you know and some of them
are radio hosts and I don't understand
how uh they're getting away with
this I worked with a guy in the private
sector who I I never met anybody who so
desperately wanted to be a CIA officer
is this guy and so he finally got
himself u in as a contractor and I said
to him so what are you doing over there
anyway and he says well uh it's it's
it's pretty Hush Hush but it's a special
intel Ops support uh special weapons and
tactics and and I'm like dude you make
yourself sound like a fool yeah because
none of those words mean
anything and you get that a lot
especially in Washington it's pretty sad
yeah I hear you I hear you I people they
trying to talk this lingo you know it's
just boots on the ground you know
exactly all the buzzword and the and the
catchphrases oh
man you know we that's like the last
nine minutes you know what do you want
to leave us with give us some advice
here well one thing that I'm really that
I'm really upset about uh since
September 11th and and this is something
that I I write about a lot and I take
very seriously and it's the loss of our
civil liberties the civil liberties of
individual Americans in the name of
National
Security when I first uh joined the CIA
we had several rules that were written
in stone and that was that the CIA did
not spy on Americans and that's the NSA
did not spy on Americans and if for
example if the NSA had accidentally
stumbled on to an American who had
accidentally um intercepted a telephone
call
every trace of that interception had to
be purged from nsa's records and then
NSA had to inform Congress oh my God
we've accidentally intercepted the phone
call or the email of an American citizen
well now nsa's primary targets are
American
citizens NSA just built a a a new
facility in the desert in Utah that has
enough storage space to save every phone
call every text message and every email
from Every American for the next 500
years we have the CIA droning American
citizens overseas as I said earlier who
have never been charged with a crime who
have never been able to face their
accusers in a court of law and uh and
there just doesn't seem to be any
outrage over this if if the the
government can kill uh you know an
American citizen overseas then can the
government kill an American citizen you
know on his Ranch in
Idaho we don't know and the Attorney
General of the United States at least
the the previous one uh Eric Holder
wouldn't even answer that question when
when asked it by uh Senator Rand Paul so
I'm just seeing a real Devolution in our
civil liberties and uh I think it's a
very uh dangerous uh Trend yeah and the
government whether or not they they
they're killing people you know know off
the street they they definitely are
throwing people in prison off the street
yeah they sure are and you can testify
firsthand and I got to tell you a good
number of my guests on this show have
been to prison you know uh and it just
seems to be a recurring uh I got former
guests that are in prison right now you
know for for nonsense
again Liberty kind of stuff you know
yeah yeah good grief I'll tell you I was
charged under the Espionage Act because
I had a conversation with a with a
reporter from The New York Times and I
said that we were torturing prisoners so
that bought me three Espionage counts um
the Espionage Act was written in
1917 to Target German sabur during the
first world war between 197 and 2009 it
was used three times but since Barack
Obama became president it's been used
nine times against Americans now none of
us none of us have been accused of of
passing information to a foreign
government to an enemy these were all
for um information that uh that went to
the press and for several of us and I'm
thinking about you know myself and Tom
Drake for example from NSA and Jeffrey
Sterling from CIA it was after we had
either reported through the chain of
command or gone public with evidence of
waste fraud abuse illegality or a threat
to Public Health or safety that's the
definition of
whistleblowing so here we are near the
end of Barack Obama's uh second uh
second term and I can safely say I think
that Barack Obama is going to go down in
history as the enemy of transparency as
the enemy of of whistleblowing and of
transparent government and that's
exactly what he said he would not do
when elected president okay that's a
good question what do you make of Barack
Obama because a lot of people I've had
on this show that have met him okay like
cynthy McKenna and Cindy shean and
others uh including a a former State
Department guy who's a K Street lobbyist
right now okay uh and when I ask them
this question you know because obviously
his paperwork and his background is
suspect he doesn't have the right
paperwork do you make him to be a
CIA
creation I've been very public with my
opinion on this and and I'll tell you
what I think has
happened you had a a very Junior Senator
a very Junior first term Senator who had
no exposure to National Security uh no
experience in National Security at all
that's exactly the kind of young new
president the CIA wants because as soon
as that new president sees his first
blue border report or black border
report something that's so many levels
Above Top Secret they can't even keep
track as soon as he's brought into his
first super secret
operation they have him hooked and
they've essentially recruited him and I
think that that is exactly what happened
to Barack Obama you know he campaigned
as an outsider he C campaigned on the
idea of of clean government and
transparency and as soon as they brought
him into the club they had
him there was a book that came out in 20
4 by Halper and hman uh two reporters uh
Time Magazine and MSNBC they had done a
report or they had done a book rather on
the 2008 election and then they did a
follow-up book on the 2012 election and
there were two quotes from Barack Obama
in that second book that were really
chilling and Obama had agreed to uh to
an interview for the book so these came
right from the horse's mouth first he
said I never told anybody I was a
liberal and I thought that was just
fascinating
the second quote was I never had any
idea I would be so good at killing
people and with that he was talking
about the Drone program and and that
tells me that that's not how he went
into his
presidency it's how he changed once he
became
president that's very interesting but uh
I had a guest on here that discussed U
some of his previous employment and uh
he described it as a a classic CIA front
operation yeah but the CIA doesn't do
stuff like that I mean they they just
that's that's the stuff of movies and
fiction books that's just not how it
works okay and and and the history with
his parents and stuff like that and
their travels and associations with
Communists and all that you don't see
anything Suspect with that either no I
don't I mean you're talking about about
a plot that would have
begun with with his birth
I mean I I don't know anybody that's
that smart or that's that good to be
able to carry out this conspiracy from
from the guy's birth all the way to the
presidency like a Manchurian
Candidate gotcha okay I really want to
have you back um to to discuss the whole
story of Abu grabe you know and all that
kind of stuff just just specifically to
get into all the details on that just uh
uh 100% specifically but once again
what's your your website oh thanks my
website is uh
www.ju.edu but you got a couple other
books you're working on too as well yeah
um I've got two books completed that are
out for bid right now one is called
letters from Loretto uh which um is
based on a series of blogs I wrote from
prison and the second one or it's the
third one I guess um it's more fun it's
it's called do doing time like a spy how
the CIA taught me to survive and thrive
in prison okay listen you got to promise
me you're going to come back all right
I'd love to thanks for having okay man
that's good stuff we got to get into
that thank you so much for coming on my
friend oh it's my pleasure thanks a lot
good night bye-bye
[Music]
oh